hey this is Mike as you and you're
listening to the brute strength podcast
this week's guest is Daniel schmuck dan
burger co-founder and director of
research and development at neuro hacker
collective a company that specializes in
developing things to improve cognitive
function they're their only product out
now is a nootropic called
qualia which is basically to supercharge
your brain and so when I went into this
conversation I had intended to talk all
about nootropics and ways to you know
what are some some legal medicines that
people can take to improve their their
brain function but what we actually
ended up talking about was first off how
- what would are basically the
prerequisites for someone to be meeting
before using these types of supplements
so we talked about adrenal fatigue and
how to know if you're drinking too much
caffeine we talked about sleep a little
bit about nutrition because the basic
premise is that if you don't have some
of these basic or all of these basics
down pat then it's like putting a
turbocharger and I'm using his wording
here a turbocharger in a car without an
engine so putting a turbocharger in a
car without an engine what means that
the car will go nowhere but if you have
an engine without a turbocharger then
your car will still move so we talked
about the engine portion of the equation
on this one and then we're going to do a
follow-up soon Daniel is an incredibly
intelligent guy and I learned a ton from
this one and I know you will too enjoy
the show what's up everyone this is Mike
cashew I'm here with Daniel 'shmock
timber ger co-founder and director of Rd
at neuro hacker collectives Daniel I
know you're an incredibly busy guy thank
you so much for making some time to do
this with me man I'm very excited happy
to be here with you this is fun awesome
so we you know before before the show
started just now we were talking about
my personal experience with cats
and the fact that I've been taking way
too much caffeine and I got off
completely for a couple weeks ago and as
we got into conversation about it it
sounds like I may need to take quite a
bit more time off
and so I thought it might be an
interesting place to start because a lot
of my listeners I know are caffeine
addicts right there's there's even a
company in the CrossFit space called and
weightlifting space called caffeine and
kilos and it's very you know
romanticized and people just love their
coffee and so I think this this would be
a really useful conversation for us to
kind of start out with for people to
know if you know they if they might need
to do the same thing that I'm about to
do so what is what are the signs that
someone is taking too much caffeine
mm-hmm so step back a little bit and
recognize that the caffeine is a
psychoactive chemical compound right we
can say it's a psychoactive drug and
it's one of humanity's favorite ones up
there with alcohol and cannabis etc for
a very long time from tea and coffee and
you know many sources and I think it's a
beautiful molecule and can actually have
life extension and life enhancing
properties used rightly and like any
tool and especially the more powerful
tool can also have life damaging
properties used improperly and it's
pretty easy to misuse caffeine the
easiest way to misuse caffeine is to use
it to deal with tiredness from not
resting enough so if someone is not
sleeping enough or they're not sleeping
well and the way they notice that is
that they're either tired in the morning
when they wake up say to in long they
don't feel fully rested or they get
tired in the afternoon their answer to
it rather than to rest is to stimulate
that's how adrenal fatigue and burnout
happens
and so we kind of paradoxically caffeine
is best used when people are already
energized and they are then using it for
enhancement of metabolic activity in an
already healthy system that can handle
the stimulus as opposed to in a under
rested under you know operating system
that can't really handle the stimulus
without damage so that's the biggest
thing and there are so many people who
use caffeine as a like as if it is a
replacement for adequate or good sleep
or good rest in other ways and that's
that is a very fast way to make it very
bad for you
right so what you're kind of suggesting
it sounds like is that one of the
biggest benefits of caffeine is more to
do with the metabolism rather than to do
with boosting your energy and
stimulating you in that sort of way is
that is that what I'm hearing when even
regarding the kind of stimulant
properties the central nervous system
stimulant properties the way it inhibits
adenosine the way that it has a
dopaminergic effect those still work
much better on a well-rested system that
can handle being stimulated without
being damaged right because if a system
is getting tired it means the body is
endogenously down regulating rather than
up regulating because it wants to be an
arrest and repair point place rather
than in a you know fully on and utilized
place so when the body needs to be an
arrest and repair place and we stimulate
it to be in a non place that is at the
cost of the integrity of the system
gotcha so that's the first big thing
with regard to caffeine is it's really
critical that caffeine is not being used
because it's needed it's being used when
it's not needed as an enhancement to the
system gods raden that's not just
caffeine that's if someone's using
nicotine so using theobromine if they're
using any kind of stimulant
it's important to eat that in mind so
before we go into how to identify if
someone is you know
taking too much of caffeine or any
stimulant why is it even important like
you know what what are the the dangers
to someone's performance and even health
yeah so many things if if you look at a
dynasty inhibition if and to adenosine
is a neuro chemical that helps bring on
the sleep impulse and so caffeine
inhibits that molecule if you're trying
to inhibit it when it's coming on strong
because it needs to come on then you'll
end up getting imbalances in your
adenosine cycle and in your circadian
cycles which will look like not getting
as good a quality sleep in not getting
it's not repaired during your sleep it
can then look like resistance to
adenosine inhibition and so you'll
notice that by having less of an effect
from coffee where you can take coffee or
any source of caffeine and still fall
asleep afterwards that means that your
ability to inhibit the adenosine cycle
is you know it's bitten down regulated
and then specifically adrenal fatigue
and adrenal burnout happens largely when
you continue to stress a system that has
been stressed and now needs to repair
before we give it adequate repair and
when you understand all of the roles of
the renal glands have in converting
neurologic impulse to endocrine impulse
you know it's involved in fat metabolism
and muscle repair and lean body muscle
mass it's involved in everything from
genetic transcription to the regulation
of the rest of the endocrine system to
immune function to bone density and so
over stimulating and over taxing your
adrenal system is definitely not
something somebody wants to do got it so
how how what are some signs were some
other signs that people can look for
where some tests they can give
themselves yeah one of the common ones
is that the stimulating effect that
caffeine had early in someone's use it
doesn't have anymore and that's the sign
of desensitization down regulation so
they used to
eight ounces of coffee and feel
increased wakefulness now they have to
drink more coffee to still notice a
smaller effect if you used to not be
able to fall asleep on coffee and now
you can fall asleep on it if you need
more than you used to need if you are
having a sense of needing it or needing
it more times in the course of a day
later into the day if you're noticing
the effects less these are all signs of
desensitization down-regulation so one
of the key things with pretty much
anything is in terms of anything that
we're taking in other than like water
and air is cycling and so just like with
workouts you need to have cycles between
stressing the muscles and then letting
them rest and repair and you want to
kind of cycle between different workouts
because if you keep doing the same
workout you start to desensitize to that
particular stimulus and you will get
less from it than if you cycle it -
another way of stressing muscle and if
you think of it from a evolutionary
point of view in terms of chemistry
coming into the body
pretty much other than water there was
no food source that was always available
all year round and so our body was
consistently getting different kinds of
chemical input and then regulating in a
hunter-gatherer kind of environment so
rotating our foods and rotating our
supplements and etc is valuable and
different ones need to rotate on
different cycles there are some things
that down regulate quickly like say some
this isn't a supplement but you know
from a from a kind of neuro hacking
point of view if someone does MDMA they
don't have to do that many times before
their system will start to acclimate to
it down regulate and then have pretty
bad symptomology if they stop doing in
so someone really shouldn't do that more
than and it's going to depend on their
individual physiology some people might
be able do it a couple times a month
some people only once every several
months so the cycle there has to be
relatively little on lots of off whereas
say someone
is taking resistant starch as a
prebiotic they can take that most of the
time but pretty much anything should be
cycled off now and again with regard to
caffeine it's it's actually a molecule
that people habituate to and then get a
low level of addiction or dependence
quite quickly which is the the signal of
that is getting headaches when you come
off of it and so letting people stay in
an on cycle longer so that they're not
dealing would say you know headaches
every week is a cycling off you know on
the weekend the general recommendation I
get to most people is if they want to
use caffeine regularly as opposed to
just now and again which i think is fine
to do if you're sleeping enough and not
overusing it is give or take one week
every quarter you come off of it and the
first couple days suck you can take a
few pro fun for headache if you need to
sleeping those first few days extra is
valuable because even if we're good
about sleep almost all of us end up
accumulating a little bits of sleep that
down again and sleep banking actually
does work to some degree so at least a
week per quarter off now if someone has
not been that for a long time so they've
been on their caffeine source regularly
for years and especially if they have
under slept in association with that and
especially if they have taken more than
caffeine than they should be to begin
with and they've pin it down regulate
their sensitivity they might need to
come off for much longer than a week
before they get to re-regulate
adequately and move back to healthy
relationship to it and depending upon
someone's caffeine metabolism which is
you know largely genetic depending upon
the health of their adrenal glands and
their nervous system that can be a
pretty huge variance but there are
people who when they cycle off of pretty
intensive caffeine usage are still
dealing with side effects of coming off
for three months Wow for the time period
that people are dealing with that it's
actually really important to not get
back on
caffeine because you really want your
system to refined its homeostasis right
to find its amino dynamics and there are
things one can do to support themselves
they can try taking other kinds of
stimulants as a way of stepping down and
then getting off those too so beaut Amin
which is a synthetic version of b1 which
effectually up regulates the sensitivity
of the d1 and d2 dopamine receptors
which are partially affected and down
regulated by the caffeine can actually
help someone come off of it faster and
easier and so bunam een and tyrosine
together often can be utilized for that
adrenal support in general B vitamins
adaptogenic herbs and mostly more than
anything is just a lot of sleep sleep
banking so when people are coming off of
having been on too much caffeine or any
kind of stimulant for a long time taking
three or four days where they just sleep
as much as they can even if that's
twelve or sixteen hours a day can make a
tremendous difference to how quickly
someone feels better their cognitive
function increases their physiologic
function increases damn well like I was
telling you before I only took two weeks
off about a month ago and as we were
talking it sounds like my you know I've
overused caffeine to a huge extent for a
very long time and I probably have to go
back in and take some more time off and
I didn't get any headaches whatsoever
but one of the worst things for me was I
was just incredibly irritable like the
smallest things would would agitate me
or stress me out I felt just this
enormous amount of pressure when nothing
had changed other than I stopped
drinking coffee it was it was a crazy
feeling right yeah coming off of
caffeine is again it's going to be much
harder for some people based on genetics
and others much harder for some people
based on how dependent they were on it
factoring all those things how long
they've been doing it
they were doing adrenal exhaustion but
in the cases where someone's dependence
on it is stronger caffeine Informer is a
good website and they give a good
breakdown of caffeine in different
products and science around caffeine
metabolism etc but if you read on there
even though they're a website that you
know is supportive of people
understanding caffeine and the positives
of it well when you read about the
experiences of people who are going
through withdrawals and come downs many
of them sound a lot like people coming
off of stronger stimulants like meth in
terms of experiencing irritability
anxiety and then worse even
depersonalization D realization so and
just to kind of step back from chemo
caffeine for a minute
like even meth is a cool molecule it's
one that again people regulate too so
quickly and it creates it creates
override independence in the
dopaminergic system so quickly and so
many side effects I just really don't
recommend but no it was used so widely
in in the you know 50 G's before we
recognized all the issues of it and and
adderall now is an impediment it's just
you know the only different
methamphetamine and adderall is one
methyl group but like all of these
things have the possibility of positive
therapeutic application take exercise
right people can exercise in ways where
they exceed what their body should do
and they injure themselves rather than
benefiting themselves and so pretty much
anything even if it can be good for you
or really is good for you in most
applications can also be used
irresponsibly and the more powerful
something is the more one has to be
mindful and the less one has been
mindful the higher the probability that
there has been something responsible use
right I love that perspective I
appreciate that I'm gonna I'm going to
give it another shot so what I want to
dive into
neuro hacking the company you own is
called neuro hacker collective and I
think everyone out there has heard of
the term neuro hacking but I think there
probably a lot of misunderstandings and
myths surrounding the word so first off
can you just describe briefly what neuro
hacking is so we'll describe the way
that we think of it and kind of how we
define it so neural hacking for us is
utilizing any kinds of tools
technologies processes they have the
ability to up regulate some aspect of
brain or nervous system function or
associated body function that then
affects brain or nervous system function
largely for the purpose of being able to
up regulate some aspect of cognitive or
emotional function we're specifically
looking at the mind brain interface
mostly now we could of course look at
the brain just for its effect on the
body like increased coordination and you
know sentry systems motor systems and
that's also kind of in the periphery of
it we're largely looking at how do we
support the body to affect the mind and
emotions also can we do with mind and
emotions to affect the body and brain
and how do we kind of hack the mind
brain interface for both better
subjective experience and increased
capacities and how do we do it in ways
that are not just upregulating to some
capacity in the moment but with side
effects and down regulation of something
meaningful long-term but how do we do it
in a way that is sustainable
regenerative and we're actually more
focused on up regulating regulatory
capacity itself rather than just up
regulating some particular kind of
stimulus in a way that might override
the integrity of the system what do you
mean can you explain that last bit a
little bit further sure so let's say
we're going to talk about stimulants
again stimulants are tools of neural
hacking but most of them most of them
don't fit it to what
would consider good neural hacking tools
so let's say we take adderall there are
outside of its medical application there
are many people who take adderall or
other kinds of smart drugs stimulants to
be able to launch their tech startup to
get to their taxes to do their midterms
or finals whatever it is because they're
having a hard time focusing adequately
and this is a helping them so adderall
is primarily working on your dopamine
system it's a presynaptic dopamine
agonist so it's making your neurons
produce more dopamine and dopamine is
involved in the ability to focus and
drive right so if you're trying to do
something that is kind of easy to
procrastinate and get distracted from
increased focus and Driver pretty great
now how does the body naturally produce
and regulate dopamine right if we think
of what we call the endogenous
dopamine's
regulatory system or the internal
dopamine regulatory system there's a
whole lot of things that happen right
you eat protein that contains phenyl
alanine the phenyl alanine is a protein
have to get digestive get absorb to the
gut the phenylalanine converts to
tyrosine converts to an acetyl tyrosine
converts to l-dopa converts to dopamine
goes across a synapse passes a bunch of
enzymes that are trying to break it down
mao-b comt etc gets received into some
postsynaptic neurons there's like
there's a bunch of things that happen to
have a regulated dopamine process and we
don't want kind of peak dopamine all the
time right if you are wanting to have
kind of intense focus concentration
recognize patterns the body will
naturally up regulate dopamine for that
purpose if you're wanting to relax and
meditate calm down make love participate
in some art you might want dopamine to
drop a lot I want serotonin to come up
right so your body is naturally
regulating all of these chemicals in
relationship to what's actually adaptive
to the environment what's going on now
so that regulatory cycle has the ability
to pay attention to what's needed and
then up or down regulate levels of
anything and anything in relationship
with everything else that's going on now
if I just
give someone a presynaptic dopamine
agonist if I give someone something that
just basically is going to kind of
elevate their dopamine and fix it then a
few things happen one they're no longer
as adaptive to their environment because
their dopamine is not being internally
regulated it's being externally
regulated which is why I love people on
any kind of psychiatric meds it even if
it stabilizes them that they describe is
oftentimes feeling more numb because now
their neuro chemistry and thus their
emotional state is more than independent
of what's happening so they don't feel
their own ability to kind of respond to
and react to and feel what's happening
right that's not desirable one of the
other things that's happening if we kind
of just fix the dopamine if the dopamine
is elevated irrespective of all the
things that it should exist in specific
ratios in dynamic equilibrium with so
the relationship of dopamine to them the
other catecholamines norepinephrine
epinephrine and it's relationship then
on the other side the neuro inhibitory
side to serotonin we did mess of all
those intentionally so now we start
getting kind of weird imbalances in
neuro chemistry and then because we're
just elevating that enchain molecule and
being able to keep it elevated the
body's own ability to produce dopamine
without it can start to drop which is
what creates dependence we call
addiction and the body's ability to the
way its processing dopamine changes so
if dopamine starts being very high
ongoingly
without the body having produced it in
the synapse then the body might start
down regulating the dopamine receptor
sensitivity because there's too much
coming through and then if you get off
of the adderall or meth or whatever it
is now the natural amount of dopamine
you produce is less than it was before
and your receptors are even less
sensitive to dopamine because there was
these higher amount now you're
experiencing this pretty terrible
withdraw and crash and so rather than
just give someone a state we want to
support their own brain body mind
capacity to produce
states that are relevant in response to
the environment in real-time so that's
what we mean by up regulating the
regulatory capacity of the system rather
than overriding the regulatory capacity
to just fix a specific state so
something like adderall yes let's just
take adderall so something like adderall
will will go in and produce a ton of
basically fill the brain with dopamine
release all of it at once and then leave
it in worse shape than it was in in the
first place and what you're kind of
suggesting or what you what you guys are
working on is things that can leave the
brain and a better and better shape than
when you found it yeah I mean when you
think about I know your audience is a
very connected to the CrossFit world and
if you think about the philosophy of the
CrossFit world and the sense of general
preparedness and general capability for
lots of different kinds of activity the
whole goal is increasing the
adaptiveness of the being physically
right that it is not someone that can
just lift a lot of weight but can barely
move or someone that could run fast but
couldn't handle weight when it can come
or it's a sense of kind of how do we
make the being actually more responsive
more adaptive increase the responsive
capacity and so there's ways of both
stressing the system and then allowing
it to repair and then stressing it in
different ways and so similarly with our
own internal physiology with our immune
system we want an immune system that can
respond better to different kinds of
pathogens faster we want a repair system
that can repair different kinds of
injury faster right we want a
neurochemical system that when we want
to focus can go into intense focus but
when we need to be able to move our
focus between a lot of things task
switching we can move it between a lot
of things without feeling stressed or
irritated by something moving our
attention so how do we increase our
overall adaptiveness as a being now of
course neural hacking doesn't imply that
a lot of like just if you're doing
anything that is changing the way the
nervous system operates for some
no purpose that's a broad definition of
neuro hacking I'm just taking the next
steps to say the kind of neuro hacking
we actually value and respect is the
kind that went while it is enhancing
some instantaneous capacity it is also
in enhancing long-term capacity or at
minimum not damaging it love it I've got
a two-part question for you next so
first off before before we get deeper
into optimizing brain function what are
what are some of the prerequisites that
people should be doing consistently
before considering some of these neuro
hacking supplementation these ways of
supplementing and if they are not
meeting those prerequisites are things
like nootropics neuro hacking
supplementation it are they even
beneficial mm-hmm
and so with those prerequisites I'm
talking I'm talking nutrition and
lifestyle mainly sure it's a nuanced
question so I'm going to answer it a
couple ways this the first part is I
would say to the degree that someone can
have the foundational aspects of
lifestyle be with it it's not first and
then any kind of enhancement be what
they built off that foundation that's a
good rule of thumb and so if someone for
instance isn't sleeping well either they
aren't getting dropping into deep Delta
sleep or they aren't getting enough
sleep
then a the starts taking immune support
of herbs well most of the immune repair
only happens at night when sleeping and
sharing Delta sleep if you're not
getting enough Delta sleep those are
just not going to do that much if you're
taking things that are going to support
a tissue synthesis most of the tissue
repair happens during Delta sleep if
you're taking the topics that are going
to support things like memory memory
consolidation happens during Delta sleep
and
some aspects happen during SATA sleep
and so you're going to get a kind of
tiny fraction of anything that you're
taking that's going to help your
regenerative capacity if you're not
doing the foundational thing that is
where regeneration occurs we can also
look at diet and say alright say I'm
going to take some supplements and I
take even if I take a handful of pills a
day I'm still talking about a relatively
tiny amount of grams in comparison to
the total amount of food I eat per day
and all of that food is chemistry that
is not just macros that are competing my
body fat muscle composition but they are
all of the microbes that are affecting
what my brain is made out of what my
hormones are made out of what all my
tissues are made out of themselves and
so all of that food is either medicine
or toxicity or somewhere on that
spectrum and so if somebody is taking in
food that is not providing adequate
nutrition and especially if it's
providing toxicity and then they're
going to try and just override that by
taking supplements it's kind of like
taking caffeine instead of sleeping
right it's just so the reason that the
word supplement is used as it means in
addition to right so if you think about
maybe I think most people in your
podcast will pray be familiar with this
if you think about the way that like a
turbocharger or supercharger added to an
engine moves more oxygen through the
engine so you can get more combustion a
turbocharger without an engine doesn't
do anything at all right innately an
engine without a turbocharger still does
a lot and so if you think of the engine
as lifestyle and you think about all the
kind of hacking as like adding a badass
turbocharger there's no question it can
make you go a lot faster but it has to
be on top of foundation otherwise it
just doesn't work that well so now
that's that's the main thing I would say
into the foundations everybody knows
what the foundations are nobody likes to
hear about them because they're hard and
we don't really like doing them and we
want like new shit
but I'm going to put to the
sleep exercise movement food diet
nutrition stress management reduction
and you know those kinds of categories
uh we can get into more things that you
could fit in there but let's just let's
just call those kind of the primary
foundational categories I'm going to put
sleep in its own category and say that
if someone is having even the tiniest
bit of sleep deficit it has a degree of
negative effect on their whole system
that a little bit of poor nutrition or a
little bit of inadequacy and exercise
just doesn't have got it interesting and
so as I mean we know that exercise
affects the genetic transcription
pattern of thousands of genes that's a
huge fucking deal it's like our genome
doesn't really matter that much genetic
transcription matters because if you
have a gene that's kind of sitting there
quiet even if it does code for elevated
homocysteine or whatever it doesn't
matter right it only matters if it's
actually coding those those proteins are
being built so you can change what is
actually expressing genetically from
lifestyle factors and so exercise you
know profoundly if you're if you're
looking at being able to affect
thousands of genes that's a huge deal
it's affecting exercise can up regulate
BDNF which is brain derived neurotrophic
factor up regulates the production of
new neurons in your brain which prevents
neurodegenerative disease repairs nerve
damage increases cognitive emotional
capacity I mean like if you've made a
list of all things exercise can do and
its effects on decreasing depression and
decreasing likelihood for every kind of
major chronic illness it's hard to
imagine anything could be more powerful
than that in the same a diet when you
think about all the negative effects of
excessive sugar of so many kinds of
processed foods of toxins that can be in
foods of employment or foods and the
positive effects of having
your micronutrients be adequate adequate
minerals vitamins etc yeah there's
nothing like all of these categories are
foundational if you get really great
sleep but eat shitty you'll have
problems if you get you know really
great exercise need shitty you'll have
problems like there none of them replace
the other ones but you will get more
profound problems faster from sleep
issues than any of the other ones so I
really do think and it's such an easy
one it's such an easy one to cut because
it's just boring and life is interesting
in this a lot of shit we want to do and
it's so easy to have this like I'll
sleep when I'm dead so give me more
caffeine like I want to do stuff one of
the things that is fascinating to me is
in the sleep deprivation studies as
someone is in moving into deeper degrees
of sleep deprivation in time so what one
thing that's very interesting say
someone naturally wakes after 8 hours
sleep and so instead they set their
alarm and they were going to get to bed
on time but they like check one last
email or did one thing so they now they
just got seven and a half hours sleep
that still seems like a lot a lot of
people when you get sick 7 a half I'm
pretty good but it's actually a half
hour sleep debt if you add that up times
a lot of nights right it doesn't take
that very doesn't take very long for it
to be missing a whole night of sleep and
you think about how someone feels in
that case and then missing weeks of
sleep reading as it goes on time that
really happens and so we'll notice that
some of the symptoms are things like
verbal fluency and word recall if you're
looking for a word or you're looking for
a name it's kind of on the tip of your
tongue but it takes a minute to find it
that's a pretty classic sign of sleep
debt and that shouldn't be that's not
just like aging or being human or having
a high IQ that's actually a sign that
your brain is not functioning that well
and it can be from different reasons but
it's most commonly asleep that if you
just completely fucking forgot where you
parked or where you put your keys or
your phone or what you were doing last
or you know something like that
so you're short
memory has that level of capacity for
impairment that's that's not normal
that's actually a sign of dysfunction
and the most common reason for it is
sleep now it can be for other reasons it
can be new nutrition deficiency it can
be stress overload it can be exposure to
toxins neurotoxins mold etc but sleeps
the most common one and sleep helps with
all those other things so one of the
interesting things though is that as
someone is moving into sleep debt at
first they notice it and they go oh I'm
a little bit tired if they had been
sleeping well and then they're like oh
I'm getting more tired but as someone
gets deeper into sleep debt they stop
recognizing that they're getting deeper
into sleep debt and so there is actually
a mismatch between someone's own
self-assessment of how much sleep debt
is there and how much like that's
actually there it's very much like drunk
people who can't recognize how drunk
they are because their brain is Mis
assessing it the tired brain is Mis
assessing this also from just an
evolutionary adaptation right like think
about mothers who have an infant baby
they're just not going to get enough
sleep for a while right unless unless
they just have one of those magical
babies that sleeps all night long and
they have a husband that does a lot
maybe a nanny in a community they're
going to go through a period of sleep
that and so to be aware of how much they
were in sleep that would just suck so
they just kind of be there's this
evolutionary adaptation to be less aware
of it but the problem of course is that
we can then exploit that lack of
awareness to keep going and so most
people will have a situation where
they're like say only operating at
seventy percent of capacity but they
only but they think they're operating at
ninety percent of capacity and that miss
assessment is actually the court with
the cause of a lot of problems so when
you were asking about foundations I
really do put sleep in its own category
and then next I'm going to put nutrition
and what people are taking in their
mouth I'm going to put movement I want
you know exercise will be a subset of
that and I'll put the relationship to
stress
which is going to have to do with the
relationships in their life the nature
of their work the way they create
meaning how they've processed old trauma
whether they give themselves time to
meditate journal etc do things to
process it now then we can put other
categories like someone's home
environment that's kind of a big deal if
they live in a house that say has mold
in it or they live in an environment
that's actually dangerous so they're
stressed out all the time or dealing
with physical stressors or they're
around people who are either
particularly negative or have lifestyle
habits that influence them in the wrong
direction so environment people and
physical environment can really kind of
be are you another foundational category
tell you what let's let's stop it right
there I want to pull on a couple of
those categories and yeah and I'm
realizing that we could have a four-hour
conversation and not not get through
everything I wanted to get through so
I'm just going to I'm just going to go
down a couple of these different avenues
first off the the that miss assessment
is absolutely fascinating because one of
the things I was going to bring up is
that so many people they think they're
operating at a hundred percent and when
you you know when you suggest a couple
things whether it be you know nutrition
or sleep advice they they don't really
see the point because they feel like
they are operating at a hundred percent
um I'm curious what are are there any
like kind of biggest bang for your buck
type interventions or changes that you
think most or all people should make all
is obviously not not going to work but
most people are deficient in and need to
change in their diet and their diet yes
this is a lot of things and it is there
are some things that are true across the
board and there's a lot of things
they're going to be different for
different goals and different
physiologies you had asked me previously
a question about a diet that focuses
mostly only on macros and being flexible
with it
if someone is focused on their physique
and so they want to make sure that they
are you know burning more calories than
they are consuming in a day or consuming
just enough of their big growing muscle
so they're really kind of macro focused
and being more flexible with which
macros which foods they can get their
macros from so they can actually sustain
that for a while we totally get why that
diet evolved and it is grossly under
aware of lots of things that are
relevant other than just like short-term
physique and flexibility of how one does
that right right and so I mean I correct
me if I'm wrong but I think that what
you might mean is like most people that
follow that kind of diet are uninformed
on the importance of micronutrients so a
few things
micros micronutrients is going to be the
first thing about that diet that is also
several other things welcome to you
could you potentially follow that kind
of diet but also keep in mind all of
your micronutrients kind of okay I'm
going to keep going so macros are you
know where you get calories from right
protein fat carbs and someone this is
the normal definition but someone can
also kind of think of water and fiber as
macros they're not caloric sources but
they're things you need a lot of each
day right but then your micronutrients
are your vitamins fat soluble water
soluble vitamins your minerals your
macro minerals and your trace minerals
and then all the phytochemicals and
polyphenols and enzymes and etc that
come from a natural diet and a wide
variety of natural foods you could say
well can't I just take a multivitamin
multi-mineral and not kind of worry
about that I would say that's better
than not doing it and a far away from
actually having a evolutionarily
relevant diet because the form of
nutrients from
natural sources let's just say from a
plant source it could be plant or animal
source you'll have a plant that has a
mineral that is bound in multiple
different forms so you know you're not
just going to be dealing with say salary
you'll have you'll have sodium as a
little bit of sodium chloride and sodium
bicarb and sodium by phosphate and you
know many different forms you'll have
you take a magnesium supplement and
maybe it's magnesium citrate the body
has give or take 13 different forms of
magnesium that we know of that utilizes
and very differently in different kinds
of tissues so magnesium for brain health
versus magnesium for its kind of
electrolyte properties or in muscles or
heart or adrenals different forms
natural foods do a better job of giving
you a wider variety of those things also
often times with cofactors some of which
won't be in the multi some of which we
don't even understand that well that
will affect absorption and then things
that we don't even usually think of as
micros like all of the antioxidants and
all the polyphenols all of the
plant-based enzymes etc so those matter
a lot and what we know about life
extension right now kind of the best
thing we still know about life extension
we know you know quite a few things is
caloric restriction is meaningful for
life extension in all mammals including
humans and but when we look at the
people from Blue Zones who have who
lived the oldest the areas where you
have the most people that live over 100
there their diets can be a little bit
different but one of the commonalities
is that there they are in general taking
in less calories than we are there in
slight caloric deficit but they're
taking their calories from micronutrient
rich sources so their diet is lower in
macronutrients higher and micronutrients
which means they you know are in caloric
restriction
being a nutrient restriction interesting
got it which is the exact opposite of
empty carbs right so this is why getting
food from organic biodynamic local
seasonal rotating whole food etc sources
actually makes a big difference as all
of those other compounds now that's one
thing right is that actually getting the
good things from food love it macros is
really important one on the other side
not getting bad things from food is also
really important and not getting bad
things from food means inflammatory
compounds so if and this is going to be
a little bit the same for everyone and a
little bit different most people will
have inflammatory reactions or have a
probability of having inflammatory
reactions from a lot of common things so
pasteurized dairy hybridized grains
excessive sugar etc those are all going
to be probably inflammatory for most
people and you're not just talking about
inflammation in the joint you're talking
about internal inflammation throughout
like systemic throughout the body right
yes starting in the gut and then having
systemic effects that originate in the
gut and other are there is there
anything any kind of identifying markers
that people can look for it yeah yeah
rather than than just going to a lab
uh-oh I thought you were asking lab
markers that's okay too yeah yeah the
easiest the easiest first so again this
is tricky because there are a lot of
different inflammatory markers and
different ones show up first for
different people
so the inflammatory markers that in a
normal non-functional medicine doc will
most commonly run is the run CRP and sed
rate and maybe homocysteine and those
are primarily kind of cardiac
inflammatory markers that are
predispositions for heart disease there
are plenty of people that actually have
full-blown inflammatory diseases where
none of those are elevated they we might
see calprotectin elevated showing
inflammation in the bowels and we can
have kind of inflammatory bowel disease
without any about the heart and plummet
or markers we can see specific cytokines
that are elevated that are going to lead
to autoimmune diseases like lupus
rheumatoid arthritis or pebble miles or
PMR so and then there are people who
have like elevated histamine maybe just
genetically that leads to inflammation
you'd have to kind of specifically look
at that including neuro inflammation or
who have leptin sensitivity which you
can see through different markers like
like Adina pectin which lead to
sensitivity to lectin rich foods so one
thing I would say here is for people who
are interested in optimizing health
going to work with a good functional
medicine doctor who can kind of take in
their symptoms take in their goals and
then prioritize labs with them and
create customized protocols highly
recommended think about this think about
all the times you heard about someone
who got some intense headache went to
the doctor had a brain scan found out
they had a pretty serious brain tumor
and they got diagnosed a few months left
to live but they were completely
asymptomatic and that brain tumor was
growing for years similarly and whether
it's a brain tumor or tumour anywhere
else the absence of symptom does not
mean the absence of pathogenesis
you can have the development of
pathology a symptomatically for a long
time and when we're looking at
autoimmune disease when someone starts
having enough joint pain that they
actually go check it out and they get
diagnosed with rheumatism it's not
uncommon to see autoimmune antibodies or
inflammatory cytokines years and
sometimes even decades before someone
would have got that diagnosis from
symptomology why that's a big deal from
a preventive medicine point of view is
if you see the early signs of it and the
person doesn't have the symptoms it can
very easily mean they never have to get
them because you can stop and you can
prevent progress of the disease and
usually even reverse it if you know what
you're doing when you get those markers
so you know if someone is in
symptomology then obviously go tend to
it but if someone is really interested
in you know you're trying to optimize
your fitness and your energy levels and
your health right now but you want to
keep optimizing those rather than have
them you know degrade relatively rapidly
in age then having a sense of what's
really going on in your body and being
able to address things ahead of time and
have a personalized approach based on
what's actually going on for you is a
good idea and is any is just any
functional med doctor acceptable or
there are there certifications and
identifying marker marks for those
doctors that you would recommend people
seek out tricky one of the things that
is on our goal list for the for our
company is actually being able to make a
directory of functional doctors and
other kinds of therapists that can
recommend people in whatever city
someone's in based on what kinds of
trainings they've done in reviews etc
there's certainly there's certainly some
things you can look for so functional
medicine is a specific branded thing the
Institute of functional medicine is it
has very
training's and some of the better
trainings that are kind of standardized
right now you can also look at just
people who call themselves naturopathic
doctors and integrative doctors and just
kind of see if what they are doing is
relevant for what your interests are
obviously if you have some GI issues
having a integrative or functional
doctor who has some GI specialty or if
you're trying to build a lot of muscle
have one that is good at Ormond
optimization right you want to look at
whatever your goals are someone who has
some specialization and experience with
those topics and then right now the best
you can probably do is check out reviews
and then go meet them and see if you
resonate done so originally I wanted to
really dive into you know nootropics and
different neuro hacking techniques as
well as longevity but it you know for
the for most of this conversations it's
been kind of like what are the what are
the precursors people need to have down
before they consider that type of thing
which i think is a great starting place
so before before we wrap up I know
people are going to have a ton of
questions about the nutrition piece what
are one two or three resources that you
would recommend people go to that are
you know widely varied and also
digestible for for laypeople in terms of
micronutrients and and that kind of that
sort of thing mm-hmm
[Music]
I think nutrition is actually one of the
trickiest topics there is so much vested
interest and people who have kind of
authored books and just hold to a
particular ideology of the kind of food
people want to eat of the associated
morality and ethics and lifestyle and
culture elements that there are very few
topics that are less coherent across the
whole field than this one medicine does
not like within the field of Integrative
Medicine there's not
as much intense difference as there is
in foundational nutrition similarly
there's not that much difference in in
thought on sleep so I mean a classic
example is people who are in the you
know more raw food and more vegan and
more kind of calorie restriction
direction and then people who are in the
more ketogenic diet primal diet paleo
direction they both reference a lot of
well done science right and there are
really good scientists and doctors on
both sides of that and they both look at
blue zone studies but in very different
ways some of it's because it's going to
be different for different peoples
genetics for different peoples
physiology how they approach it etc so I
would say there are general rules of
thumb to say one should eat closer to
the living ecosystem is a generally good
rule of thumb meaning the more processed
and packaged hybridized sprayed etc
something is the worse it is in general
it's not an absolute truth but it's a
general truth and closer to things that
have been what our bodies evolved to eat
over very long periods of time and
particularly also with less pesticides
and herbicides and things that are
designed to kill life on them and the
more they come from healthy soils rather
than pretty demineralized soils and the
fresher they are versus they've been out
of the ground for pretty long time these
are all you know in to the degree it's
meats then grass-fed free-range etc
that's kind of important across the
board whether you're eating meats or not
or these ones are not or nitrates or not
like kind of dial that and second dial
in this general approach to things that
would have been part of a living
ecosystem first and I would say then the
next good rule of thumb is paying
attention to how you feel as pretty
closely as you eat different things so
pay attention right after
miel do you have a sense of over
fullness in your belly like you're
having a hard time digesting it do you
have GI symptoms afterwards you get
tired after eating in do you get hungry
again right away do you have energy for
a while though do you sleep well
afterwards the more you can do kind of a
really attentive quantified self
assessment just even spend a few weeks
and journal what you're eating and then
journal how you're feeling in
association and dial it in the
combination of the general rule of thumb
of eating evolutionarily relevant foods
and paying attention to which ones feel
good for you that would be foundational
then study specific diets on top of that
and then do actual functional medicine
where you look at your nutrient levels
and your you know food allergies etc on
top of that in terms of resources to go
study more the reason why I was hesitant
to say the resources is they mostly all
fall into camps that are very different
than other camps so have good things to
say so I think Dave asked freeze nubuck
headstrong is one of the best
introductions to health for people who
have not got into it yet that I'm aware
of I think it is a you know people take
different through lines of how they
write a book like that whether it's
under any healthy fats or whether it's
on the same caloric restriction the
through line he took was cellular health
mitochondrial energy and brain that's a
great through line and so then he looked
at diet and exercise and sleep and
toxicity and hacking techniques in light
of that and you know I think a lot of
what he has in the book is really
foundationally great it's not going to
be appropriate for everyone people will
want to modify but I think it's a great
starting place in terms of other people
that have a similar issue philosophy a
lot of what dr. Mercola writes on diet
is kind of similar and again clinically
well backed up if you go speak to a
normal cardiologist they're still
looking at pretty
Ken's work on extremely low fat diets
having lower heart disease living longer
and more Mediterranean diet I think that
is largely just older research but but
not irrelevant and I have seen people do
blueproof diet ketogenic diet a little
bit wrongly and have their lipid profile
gets super whacked and so there is some
need for nuance and I actually think a
lot of the raw food vegan communities
has good things to say on diet even if
you decide not to be vegan you decide to
eat some other you know animal products
with it a lot of the insights on soil
conditions and micronutrients and plants
and therapeutic use of herbs and
whatever there is great so those are a
few that's excellent
I appreciate that so it sounds like
there is no perfect diet like one size
fits all which is kind of a you know
that's that's the case in just about
everything in life right there are rules
of thumb there are generalized
principles and then there's a lot of
room for adaptation like what someone
should eat if they are training heavily
versus not and training for powerlifting
versus ultramarathons
and you know based on their genetics and
age and what kind of medical conditions
they have that's all going to just be so
so different one thing I will also say
is be the idea that someone should not
do kind of more advanced neuro hacking
biohacking things if they don't have the
foundations down this is not totally
correct I wanted to take that
perspective first because I wanted to
emphasize foundations but say we look at
either use of no tropics or you said EEG
neurofeedback or different kinds of
sleep tech sometimes even if someone's
foundations are screwed they're screwed
enough that the person's behavioral
chemistry is out of whack enough that
they just can't fix it it can't actually
get themselves to eat better exercise
well you know sleep well regularly
enough
and sometimes those interventions
actually help the person enough that not
only do they get the benefit of that
intervention but it helps them get the
Foundation's down better to change their
behavior right absolutely so like one of
the things that you know we have found
with you know with quality and
nootropics is if people are having
issues with sleep if their underslept or
if they have kind of overuse stimulants
they might need to fix that first
but otherwise if say their diet is poor
or their exercises poor it's been very
common that people will start I mean not
all know perfectly the same quality
specifically has a lot that balances
that dopamine opioid access so it's
actually helping work on the chemistry
systems of motivation and behavior
themselves we've had a lot of people who
just couldn't get themselves to be
regular with exercise and diet they got
on that and then they actually were so
the general rule of thumb is someone
does want to be focused on Foundations
but if they're having a really hard time
focusing with foundations finding tools
that can not support them to keep not
doing foundations and things that they
can just augment it but things that can
actually help them with the behavioral
dynamics of doing the foundation will
work that can be super useful that's a
great perspective I love that even if it
even if it is a placebo that gets them
to change the behavior then the
important part is that they are changing
their behavior which oftentimes is the
most important piece so the fact that
what you guys do is so holistic and you
know has such a long term effects is
just that much better I love it
yeah and you know sometimes sometimes
therapy actually can the right kinds of
therapy can really help someone change
patterns underneath their behavior and
like neurofeedback can help neuro
regulatory patterns that can make a huge
difference to just someone state of
health and well-being overall stress
assessing but also then how people react
to stress and go into addictive patterns
so we can say both sides means they get
foundations first and then two advanced
techniques we can also say if the
advanced techniques can help you be able
to do a better job of foundations that
you've had this new year's goals every
year and not actually been able to
stabilize don't keep trying and failing
it the same thing see if additional
tools can support you right I love that
so look I am really dying to continue
this conversation we've opened so many
doors but we're going to have to save
some of it for the next time what what
do you have what do you want to leave
these listeners with or do you have an
ask of them I enjoyed the time with you
and I'm looking forward to the next time
and if this was interesting and people
have questions on other topics my ass
would be they just tell you what they're
interested in that we talk about next
time and other than that my ask would be
that they take more responsibility for
their own health and well-being in life
and they did previously and that means
study more so they can actually
understand how to support themselves
because that will put them not just in
the best position for their own health
but also in the best position to help
other people and be an asset in the
world that's phenomenal well I'm
definitely inspired I'm going to make a
few behavioural changes and then do some
more self experimentation with quality
myself and then once that is taking
place then we'll then we'll follow up
again done good conversation thank you
so much Daniel this has been phenomenal
man
likewise appreciate it alright brother
bye hey guys I'm going to invite any of
you that are interested to call into a
voicemail that I have set up and leave
some questions so then I'm going to play
back your question on the podcast and
I'm either going to answer the question
myself or I'm going to get one of my
guests to help me answer those questions
if you're interested the number is 8 Oh
one four four nine oh five oh three
that's 801 four 4905 oh three